<?xml version="1.0"?>
<blog>
	<post slug="emotional-music" category="articles" date="2013-10-26">
		<title>Using emotional music to make an impact</title>
		<content>
			<figure>
				<img src="/media/binary-sunset.jpg" alt="The &quot;Binary Sunset&quot; scene in Star Wars: A New Hope" class="wide"/>
			</figure>

			<p>As roleplayers, we are used to adventures that focus on violent conflict and stressful situations. Movies and books, however, generally put much more emphasis on human emotion than traditional roleplaying games. Even adventure movies like <i>Star Wars</i> devote entire scenes to the thoughts and feelings of the characters. Gamemasters who want to incorporate the same type of scenes in their games can benefit immensely from emotional music.</p>

			<p>In this context, emotional music refers to the type of music that plays in a movie or game when the characters' feelings, rather than their actions, are in focus. These feelings can be anything from sadness and despair to love and relief. Two common traits of such music are a lower tempo and the use of certain instruments like the violin and the piano. Notable examples include "Binary Sunset" from <i>Star Wars: A New Hope</i> and the opening theme to <i>The Rock</i>.</p>

			<p>Emotional music requires special attention because emotional scenes, as mentioned earlier, are an unexpected part of adventures for many roleplayers. Merely describing an emotional situation is not guaranteed to evoke emotion among the players in the way that simply rolling for initiative will evoke an instinctive feeling of excitement. Likewise, merely playing emotional music will not necessarily have the same effect as playing action music. In a game where emotional scenes are rare, the combination of emotional narration and emotional music can be crucial in properly setting the mood.</p>

			<p>A good example is a recent session of <i>Fiasco</i>, which primarily consisted of action scenes interspersed with dialogue and investigation. In <i>Fiasco</i>, which embraces dark humor, players often react to tragic fates with indifference or even amusement. This is especially true in the very last montage scene of a session, where characters usually face disaster and tragedy of some sort. For this particular session, however, I had decided to experiment with my usual repertoire of calm, suspenseful, and stressful music by adding emotional music to the mix.</p>

			<p>When the time came for the characters to meet their grim ends, we started the emotional music—and something changed. Instead of simply thinking that the characters got what they deserved or even being amused by their failure, we found ourselves feeling sympathy for them—even for those who were clearly villains in the story. If this is the level of emotion that can be achieved in a morally ambiguous setting like <i>Fiasco</i>, it is easy to imagine how powerful emotional music can be in the epic tales of good and evil that are common in other roleplaying games.</p>

			<p>Apart from conveying emotion in a scene that has already started, emotional music can also be used for setting expectations of a scene to come. If the gamemaster plays emotional music while the characters are exploring the debris of a burned-down village, the players are much more likely to contemplate the tragedy of what has happened than watch for hidden enemies or search for loot.</p>

			<p>Emotional scenes can be demanding and risk feeling out-of-place, so you might find yourself wanting to save them for a select few moments in your sessions. In such a moment, however, emotional music can help you create the most memorable scene of an entire campaign.</p>

			<p class="appendix"><a href="mailto:rpg.ambience@gmail.com">Send in your thoughts</a> about using emotional music and your comments might be featured in the article.</p>
		</content>
	</post>
	<post slug="jade-empire" category="music" date="2013-10-10">
		<title><i>Jade Empire</i> (oriental)</title>
		<content>
			<figure class="cover-art">
				<img src="/media/jade-empire.jpg" alt="Cover art for the Jade Empire soundtrack"/>
			</figure>
			
			<p>While the soundtrack of <i>Jade Empire</i> is sadly one of few readily available soundtracks from games with an oriental setting, it's useful enough that it might just be the only one you need. The calmer tracks draw heavily from Chinese aesthetics while the most dramatic tracks are closer to traditional orchestral arrangements. There are 31 tracks in total, and many of them are uniform enough to be useful without any editing.</p>
			
			<h2>Suggested scenes</h2>
			
			<h3>Pre- and post-game</h3>
			<ol>
				<li value="1">The Way of the Open Palm</li>
				<li value="2">Jade Empire Main Theme</li>
			</ol>

			<h3>Calm</h3>
			<ol>
				<li value="3">Hills and Fields / Dance of the Babbling Brook / Fallow Ground</li>
				<li value="5">Dawn Star Theme</li>
				<li value="23">Silk Fox Theme</li>
				<li value="26">Sky Theme</li>
				<li value="31">Sanctuary</li>
			</ol>

			<h3>Mystery</h3>
			<ol>
				<li value="9">Buried Secrets / Whispers</li>
				<li value="10">Mischief in the Marsh</li>
				<li value="15">House of Spirits / The Dark Land</li>
				<li value="17">3 Winds</li>
				<li value="22">Last Rites / Internment</li>
			</ol>

			<h3>Action</h3>
			<ol>
				<li value="4">Fist / Test Your Mettle</li>
				<li value="7">Fury, Hammer and Tongs</li>
				<li value="20">Into the Fray</li>
			</ol>

			<h3>Epic action</h3>
			<ol>
				<li value="11">Empire at War</li>
				<li value="14">Fires of Chaos</li>
				<li value="29">Soaring / Stormclouds</li>
				<li value="30">Torment / The Way of the Closed Fist</li>
			</ol>

			<h3>Party</h3>
			<ol>
				<li value="6">The Tea House</li>
				<li value="13">A Night Out</li>
				<li value="18">Ballad of the Drunken Revelers</li>
				<li value="24">Wine and Women</li>
			</ol>
		</content>
	</post>
	<post slug="pre-and-post-game-music" category="articles" date="2013-10-10">
		<title>Enhancing sessions with pre- and post-game music</title>
		<content>
			<figure>
				<img src="/media/kung-fu-fighting.jpg" alt="The cover of &quot;Kung Fu Fighting&quot; by Carl Douglas"/>
			</figure>
			
			<p>It is well known that the opening and closing scenes of a movie can be greatly enhanced by music, and doing the same for your roleplaying games is one way of using RPG Ambience. Both moviegoing experiences and roleplaying sessions, however, actually start before the opening scene and end after the closing scene.</p>
			
			<p>The real start of the experience is when the audience members arrive—in the cinema or at the gaming table—and it really only ends when they have left. During all of this time before and after the main attraction, the audience will be enthusiastically discussing their expectations, their impressions, and their hopes for possible sequels. Movie directors have no way of influencing this important part of the experience, but gamemasters do, and one effective way of doing so is by playing music before and after the adventure itself.</p>

			<p>The idea behind using pre- and post-game music is to promote a certain mood that you want the players to be in while they are creating their characters or recapping the previous session, as well as when they are discussing the game right after it has finished. The music can simply reinforce themes that are important to the adventure itself, such as starting a horror session with dark, ominous music to get the players in the mood. Conversely, it can also provide contrast, such as ending that same horror session with upbeat music in order to take the edge off the situation.</p>
			
			<p>The common idea is that you can influence your players to think about the game—and to think about it in a certain manner—even while they're not playing it.</p>

			<p>Since pre- and post-game music takes place outside of the adventure itself, it doesn't have to relate directly to any events taking place in-game. This gives you some creative freedom and allows you to select music that would otherwise be difficult to fit into a session.</p>

			<h2>How to select pre- and post-game music</h2>
			
			<p>For pre-game music, suitable tracks include epic opening themes, menu music from video games, and tracks that are too varying in tempo or mood to use during the adventure itself.</p>
			
			<p>As an example, consider the first distinct piece of music that plays in the <i>Knights of the Old Republic</i> video game. The famous <i>Star Wars</i> opening theme doesn't actually appear until after the player has created his character; during the entire character creation process, the music played is the theme of the Old Republic. This epic composition is too anthemic to easily fit inside an adventure, yet not powerful enough to serve as the adventure's opening theme (which in any <i>Star Wars</i> game is a given). As pre-game music, however, it works perfectly to give the players a sense of epic adventure coupled with the uniquely ancient feel that accompanies games set in this era.</p>
			
			<p>For post-game music, you have even more leeway in selecting your tracks, because you don't risk setting the wrong tone for an entire session. Unless your campaign is of a very serious nature, you can even consider using humorous, silly, or even modern-day tracks that tie into the story that you were telling.</p>
			
			<p>For a recent one-shot game <a href="http://www.bullypulpitgames.com/news/2011/03/01/march-playset-of-the-month-quest-for-the-golden-panda/">set in mythical China</a>, I ended the session with the well-known '70s song "Kung Fu Fighting" by Carl Douglas, also notably used in the movie <i>Kung Fu Panda</i>. It's light-hearted, anachronistic, and downright silly, and using it in-game would have ruined the mood, but playing it after the adventure made perfect sense. If you're not prepared to go that far, look for setting-appropriate music that reinforces the overall experience of the players, such as an upbeat orchestral composition for a session that saw the characters prevail in an epic battle.</p>

			<p>Even if you put a lot of effort into selecting pre- and post-game music, it may not make an obvious difference at the gaming table itself. That's alright, because the main goal of using pre- and post-music is to affect players subtly, or even subconsciously. If the players start to find themselves feeling that the gaming experience starts as soon as they enter the gaming room, and only ends just after they have left it, you're doing things right.</p>

			<p class="appendix"><a href="mailto:rpg.ambience@gmail.com">Send in your thoughts</a> about using pre- and post-game music and your comments might be featured in the article.</p>
		</content>
	</post>
	<post slug="overlap" category="articles" date="2013-10-10">
		<title>Achieving near-seamless audio loops with the overlap feature</title>
		<content>
			<p>An important feature for GMs who use music during their games is the ability to have it loop without interruptions and jarring transitions. When I first started developing RPG Ambience, my intent was to achieve this by implementing seamless looping of tracks. I quickly encountered two major problems:</p>

			<ol>
				<li>First of all, completely seamless looping of audio files does not have good browser support (if any).</li>
				<li>Second of all, and most importantly, very few music tracks have endings that line up with the beginning, making the transition very noticeable even when it's made seamless.</li>
			</ol>

			<p>With this in mind, I began considering an alternative to seamless looping that is available in some media players: crossfading, which is achieved by fading out the old track while simultaneously fading in the new one. I was optimistic that this approach would be the best and most realistic alternative to truly seamless looping. After manually trying the technique on some tracks, however, I was not completely satisfied; the transition was still very much noticeable for many tracks.</p>

			<p>After a while, I started experimenting with what I at first thought to be a "poor man's" crossfading: to simply have the new track start a bit before the old track ended, without fading either of them. In earlier versions of RPG Ambience, this was called <dfn>crossover</dfn>, but it has since been renamed <dfn>overlap</dfn>. This turned out to be a very useful technique that consistently matched the quality of crossfading and often exceeded it, many times even achieving unnoticeable transitions.</p>

			<p>The two waveforms below show the difference between an audio loop using crossfading and one using overlap:</p>
			
			<div class="side-by-side">
				<figure>
					<figcaption>Crossfading</figcaption>
					<img src="/media/crossfading.png" alt="Waveform of a sample transition using crossfading"/>
					<audio src="/media/crossfading.ogg" controls=""></audio>
				</figure><!--
				--><figure>
					<figcaption>Overlap</figcaption>
					<img src="/media/overlap.png" alt="Waveform of a sample transition using overlap"/>
					<audio src="/media/overlap.ogg" controls=""></audio>
				</figure>
			</div>
			
			<p>While the loop using crossfading sounds alright, there is still a noticeable gap between the end of the old track and the beginning of the new track, and the distinct opening drum beat is lost in the fading. The loop using overlap, on the other hand, continues playing the song without even skipping a beat, and retains the opening drum beat.</p>

			<h2>How to use overlap in RPG Ambience</h2>

			<p>This brings us to the implementation of overlap in RPG Ambience. In order to make your audio tracks loop using overlap, go to the <i>Sound</i> tab of a scene and look for the <i>Overlap</i> field at the bottom. This input controls how many seconds early the new track will start before the old track ends. Fractional numbers are allowed, but note that very short durations may not work as intended; due to technical limitations, a value of less than roughly 0.3 might effectively be rounded down to zero.</p>

			<p>It's important to note that the <i>Overlap</i> setting in the current version of RPG Ambience applies to all track transitions for that scene. In other words, it's not currently possible to specify that one track should start three seconds early and another track should start five seconds early. I have thought about expanding this functionality in the future, but in absence of such a feature, my experience tells me that a blanket overlap duration of about 2-5 seconds is usually enough to achieve a pretty good result.</p>

			<p>One final note: If the overlap doesn't seem to take effect properly, make sure that your audio files don't begin or end with long silences, as some recordings do. A sound editor like <a href="http://audacity.sourceforge.net/">Audacity</a> can be used to remove those parts from your files.</p>
		</content>
	</post>
</blog>